Okay, now for the record, not clickbait.
Keric energy does not equal a half MV squared,
sort of in some situations anyway.
Look, it's been real busy around here
and stand up mass world.
Oh my goodness, we're doing videos of ridiculous scale.
We're putting something on the moon for crying out loud.
We're renovating the new studio, the new deal,
which is why we had to make do here
in this temporary studio, pseudo-rio, temporary space.
And when I came across this fun fact about kinetic energy,
now it's not a half mb-squared.
I thought you know what?
Quick, easy fun video where I'll just show you,
first of all, why we think it's a half mb-squared,
and I'll show you why it's not.
Before we get into the derivation proper,
we have to define some terms.
what is kinetic energy?
First thing out of energy, something's got
because it's moving.
That's why things hurt if they're throwing at you.
For example, plasterboard for hilarious joke.
But yeah, something's not moving.
No kinetic energy.
You start moving your player force.
You do some work.
It starts moving.
And that's, I mean, the technical physics definition.
It's kind of just the total amount of work
that's been done to an object.
What's work?
perfectly good physics word that physicists have decided actually means if you keep track
of the amount of force you're applying to something and the distance is traveling as
you do that.
So actually, you know what, let's just start writing some stuff down here.
So your kinetic energy equals the total amount of work and that equals if we sum up all of
that force over distance. So that's going to be an integration of the force for applying
dx. Now, okay, let me draw the diagram here. So you've got a surface with some kind of object
on it where applying our force to it and it starts at position x. And then, so this is like a one
dimensional direction it can move in as it goes along to a new location. So if I get dx is like
that tiny little change in direction.
So connect energy is just the integral
of the force dot dx.
Now force, we know from Newton,
is mass times acceleration.
So that equals the integration of now force
becomes mass dot a, m times a, dot dx.
Now I know me putting those dots at the bottom,
it's gonna make some of you mad.
I think I'm pretty funny.
Now, here's what we're gonna do to rearrange this.
Acceleration is just the rate of change of velocity.
So in fact, that A equals dV dt.
So I'm gonna substitute dV dt for A,
except I'm gonna move the dt
over to the side.
So it equals mass times instead of acceleration dV dot,
and now I'm going to have the dx over dt.
And what is dx dt?
Where's the rate of change of position is velocity.
So that dx dt becomes v.
This whole thing equals integrating mass times velocity times dv.
And now it's just a standard integration,
like what you might be having flashbacks to,
from when you were at school.
What can we differentiate to get v?
Well, it must have started V squared,
so we subtract one and we get V
and that two must have gone somewhere.
So it equals a half M V squared.
So if this is also obvious,
why is it not the correct answer?
Well, we're gonna try again,
but we're gonna do it with more attention to detail.
So, we'll start basically the same way.
We were right from the beginning.
Now, last time, we just replaced F the force
with mass times acceleration.
It actually, F equals DP, DT.
And P is momentum.
I mean, we're already using M for mass.
It's not ideal, I get it.
But mass times acceleration is just a way of saying
is the rate of change of momentum.
Momentum P equals MV.
That's momentum.
Ah, that is it.
It's only momentum at boring normal speeds.
You know, anything way below the speed of light.
we've forgotten about relativity.
Yes, if you're waiting for the big twist,
it's that this is actually a video about relativity,
that ridiculous physics theory where how big you are
and how much mass you get changes
based on how fast you're going.
And that's why kinetic energy isn't a half MV squared.
You got to compensate for how fast you're going compared
to the speed of light.
Now, I did a video previously that covered
special relativity and I showed how you can work out
compensating factor. It's often called gamma,
the square root of one minus,
your velocity squared,
about about a speed of light squared.
I'll link to that video below,
but now all I have to do is redo the entire working out
in far more detail, factoring that in.
And look, I'll level with you.
This is gonna take a very long time.
So I'm just gonna skip through it here.
If you do wanna watch doing things properly,
Matt, work it out,
and excruciating accurate detail.
The entire thing will be over on the second channel,
So you can pop over there and watch that if you want,
I'll link it from the end card at the end of this video.
But all you need to know here and now is we put
the gamma factor in, we crunch it through for a while,
but because it's a square root,
we've got to work that out somehow.
And I use the binomial expansion,
which gives us an infinite series of terms,
the more of which you use, the more accurate
your square root calculation is.
And so I crunch the handle on that.
And eventually, out the other side arrives
a proper equation for kinetic energy.
Okay, now you know what, I'm gonna try and just break out a little bit to see what that
D gamma MV is gonna look like.
Now mass is a constant, so we can put the mass out the front.
Okay, that all works.
Now a little bit of a detour here because you can see we've got, we've got gammas and
V's and D gammas and DV's.
We kinda wanna be able to link all these together and simplify that down a little bit.
So we get D gamma equals, so the half, this is just classic differentiation.
So in fact, we simplify that down.
It's just V on C squared outside of one minus V squared
on C squared, negative three on two.
Great.
So that equals gamma cubed V over C squared,
DV.
Okay, so now we have, we got D gamma
and we've linked that to DV by gamma cubed V on C squared.
C squared so let's get page three, start joining this all together. I'm
that's now the gamma, I'm gonna multiply that V through and the V's gonna cancel
with that one boom out of here so now it's C squared on gamma squared, love it.
All of that's going in there. It turns out the kinetic energy just equals the
integral of mass, that's all cancelled. C squared, D gamma. What we got to do is integrate
that. What are we integrating tool from? So I mean this is going to be odd but gamma doesn't
start at zero. Gamma is a function of your velocity and the velocity is zero. Gamma is 1.
So we're integrating from gamma equals one up to some gamma.
It's the total energy in the system.
Gamma mc squared minus the bit that's just the bit you get for free.
Equal to mc squared.
It's just the energy of merely being.
That is the kinetic energy.
It's going to work it out.
Surely that's going to be easy.
A problem now is we've got to deal with that gamma.
It's getting in the way.
and it contains a square root.
So we're gonna remove it using a fun side binomial fact.
Gamma equals, well we saw it before,
it's one minus v squared on c squared to the a half.
So what we're doing now is we're sitting basically
our x equals negative v squared on c squared
and our n equals a half.
Oh, forgot my negative, that's the negative a half up there.
because it's gamma's in negative.
Whoops, that's on me.
So that's, though those negatives are gonna cancel.
Woo!
Ha ha!
Thought I had negative energy there for a second.
Always check the physics.
We put it in up there minus one.
You can see the expansion starts with a one.
That's out of here.
So I'm gonna multiply all the terms by mc squared.
So the first ones are half m.
The C squareds cancel out V squared.
We got it.
It's exactly the same as before.
Oh, it's so much more complicated.
But before we got to that and it stopped.
We're like, oh, that's the end.
Just a half MV squared, no more to say.
Now we know, forget that, we know here, there's more to say.
We've got to add on these infinitely many other terms.
Because now it's also plus 3, 8s,
V to the 4 on,
it was C to the 4, C squared is going to cancel that.
C squared plus more.
So there it is.
Kinetic energy is a half MV squared,
same as before, plus plus 3, 8s.
M, feet are the 4c squared, plus another one.
I'll put it on the screen, plus that.
And then plus this one, as many as you want,
because we're using the bottom only expansion
to represent a square root.
But if you happen to do it that way,
you swap it in to represent a square root,
then out drops the classical one at the top.
That makes sense, that's the whole point.
I mean, relativity didn't replace classical,
mechanical physics.
We kept that, special relativity just said,
ah, if you're going real fast,
these these extra ones, but at slow speeds,
like as we always knew, slow speeds, this works great.
Just if you're going very, very fast,
you got a factor, you're a little bit off at high speeds,
factor in the other terms.
and we're talking real high speeds.
The fastest moving human-made object
is the Parker solar probe, the spacecraft studying the sun,
whipping around that sun.
And is it Perry Hylian?
I think that's the fastest part of the orbit.
I'd say trying to not melt,
it's going by so fast, that's why they called it Parker.
Because it's so quick.
And it's absolute max velocity.
It is going at 690,000 kilometers per hour.
That's like a lot in miles per hour, a lot.
I mean over 428,000 miles per hour.
And so obviously it's got a lot of regular
or kinetic energy, so much kinetic energy.
But is that fast enough compared to the speed of light
for the second term to kick in?
We round the numbers and there is a non-zero second term.
In fact, as a percentage of the total kinetic energy,
your relativistic kinetic energy comes in at around about 0.00000153%.
That's less than one part in a million.
It's about one part in six and a half million.
But that's not zero.
I mean, that's significant for some definition of significant.
I mean, I imagine that's probably don't have to factor it
into their calculations, but technically the fastest moving
human-made object has a noticeable,
noticeable amount of relativistic momentum,
just probably not enough.
We have to actually care about it as it's racing past the sun.
[♪ INTRO MUSIC PLAYING [♪
Other than that, I think there are some electron calculations
where you might have to factor in some of the higher order terms,
but that's pretty much it.
I mean, maybe the people that's certain,
I assume if you're working at Surn,
you'd have to use loads of those higher order factors
to get the precision of the relativistic moment.
Oh, hang on, that's just a little about it.
You got a phone call.
Oh, that's my friend Clara.
Hang on, let me just...
Hey, this is my friend Clara.
There you are.
Clara works at Surn.
Actually, Clara, do you want to introduce yourself
to the fine viewers?
Hi, yeah, my name is Clara,
and I am a particle physicist working on the Atlas experiment here at SIRN.
The beams that we use at SIRN, they are relativistic, highly relativistic.
So the large Hadron collider once it gets to top energy,
it's travelling at 99.99991% of the speed of light,
which is about five miles an hour slower than the speed of light.
For the large Hadron collider, when it's at its top energy,
we're using 6,800 GEV, so an EV is an electron volt,
and the mass of the proton is 938 MEV,
and so when we do the calculation,
we get 7,250 for agama, which is slightly bigger than one.
So how many of the higher order terms do you need to use?
So I have to be honest that we don't end up calculating them
because there's so many, yeah, none of them.
There's so many higher order calculations
that we'd have to do that to get the precision that we need.
It would just take a very long time.
So instead we work out the kinetic energy
through experimental methods also with protons
because they are not fundamental particles.
They have particles inside of them.
We don't know what the exact collision energy is for protons.
So we want to know what their energy is,
but it doesn't matter so much for the Large Hadron Collider.
If we were colliding electrons and positrons,
their antimatter counterpart,
then we want to know this more precisely
because then we want to know exactly
the energy of the collision
so we can work out what happened in the middle.
Anyway, Clara, always a pleasure to chat.
Thank you so much for phoning in with a correction.
Are you going to wave goodbye to everyone over there?
There you go.
Yeah, cheers.
So there you are, everyone.
Turns out, I guess the moral of the story there is
by no merely expansion is a terrible approximation
for a square root.
So that's it, that's the nice quick,
straightforward video.
Thanks for watching.
I've had it in clickbait you
into just watching someone do integration.
For a whole video, you're still watching.
And you've never watched one of my videos before.
Welcome aboard.
It's more of this if I'm being honest.
And is this clickbait?
I don't know, the momentum is a half mb squared.
That is still true, but sometimes,
Sometimes you need a 3-8m V to the 4 on C squared.
But not often it turns out.
And even if you do need it,
if you don't do it that way.
Nah, so I feel like today we learned nothing.
Bye.